Guide to the Cass Gilbert Collection 1883-1952 (Bulk 1900-1934 ) PR 21
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Series V. Lantern Slides
  - Subseries III: Glass plate negatives
    - Prelimary study of skyscraper, NYC (2 negatives), undated (Box 680A)
    - Drawing of construction site at waterfront, NYC, E.K. Hengerer, 1928 January (Box 680A)
- Series VI. Record Books of Drawings
  The record books contain lists of drawings issued and received by Cass Gilbert. The list assigns a number for each drawing and provides information on the date issued and received, the name of the building, the type of drawing, and a description.
  - Record Books of Drawings, 1906-1909 (Box 686)
  - Record Books of Drawings, 1909-1913 (Box 687)
  - Record Books of Drawings, 1913-1920 (Box 688)
- Series VII. Scrapbooks
  The oversize scrapbooks contain mostly clippings regarding Gilbert and his architecture projects. Many of these volumes are fragile and access is dependent upon the judgment of the print room staff.
  - Scrapbook (Clippings), 1890-1903 (Box 689)
  - Scrapbook (Clippings re Architecture), [1893-1898] (Box 690)
  - Scrapbook (Clippings and Architectural Drawings), [1886-1900] (Box 691)
  - Scrapbook (Clippings and Drawings), 1901-1909 (Box 692)
  - Scrapbook (Clippings and Drawings), 1925-1932 (Box 693)
  - Scrapbook (Newspaper Clippings), 1910-1911 (Volume 432)
  - Scrapbook (Newspaper Clippings), 1906-1911 (Volume 433)
  - Scrapbook (Newspaper Clippings), 1912-1926 (Volume 434)
- Series VIII. Metal Printing Plates
  The printing plates contain images of the Connecticut State Library, the Essex County Courthouse, the US Legation Building, Oberlin College, and the US Custom House. It also contains plates for buildings that are unidentified.
  - Connecticut State Library and Supreme Court Building, Undated (Box 694)
  - Essex County Courthouse, Undated (Box 694)
  - United States Legation Building, Undated (Box 694)
  - Oberlin College, Undated (Box 695)
  - United States Custom House, Undated (Box 695)
  - Unidentified Buildings, Undated (Box 696)
- Series IX. European Sketchbooks
  This series contains the sketchbooks of architecture that Gilbert studied in Europe. The drawings specifically depict the architecture of England, Italy, France, Spain, Germany, Austria, and the Lowlands.
  - Sketchbook of European Architecture, 1880 (Volume Vol.1)
  - Sketchbook of European Architecture, 1898 (Volume Vol.2)
  - Sketchbook of Ironwork in London, 1920 (Volume Vol.3)
  - Sketchbook of Spanish Architecture, 1925 (Volume Vol.4)